A Finding Aid to the Dorr Bothwell Papers, 1900-2006, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bothdorr
Archives of American Art
- Personal Business Records, 1925-2006; Series 3; (Box 3-4; 0.7 linear feet)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for the M. H. De Young Memorial Museum, 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for M. Lee Stone Fine Prints, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for the Riverside Art Center and Museum, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for the San Francisco Art Institute Art Bank, 1959-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for the San Francisco Museum of Art Rental Gallery, 1941-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for Serigraph Galleries, Inc. through the National Serigraph Society, 1946-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for the Tobey C. Moss Gallery, 1988-1999; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 76-77)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for William P. Carl Prints and Drawings, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Consignment/Sales Records for Miscellaneous Galleries, 1940-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Card File of Exhibitions, 1925-1947 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Exhibition Entry Cards, 1947-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Receipts for Art Work Sales, 1946-1990 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Notebook of Receipts for Artwork Sales, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Travel Receipts, 1951-1982, undated; (7 folders) (Box 4, Folder 2-8)
  - Medical Receipts, 1982-1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1956-1997, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pollock-Krasner Foundation Grant Material, 1995-2001; (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 11-15)
  - Estate Materials, 1997-2006; (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 16-20)
- Notes and Writings, 1928-1998; Series 4; (Box 4, 11, 14, 15; 0.8 linear feet)
  Notes and writings include five diaries containing brief daily entries, one journal written during travel in Japan, England, and Mexico, a second journal from a trip to London and Paris, guest books for an exhibition and for various parties including Bothwell's 80th and 90th birthdays, mailing lists, lists of faculty, students, and schedules of classes for various organizations including the Sierra Club, and Artists Equity, and art schools including the Ansel Adams Yosemite Workshop, and Creative Images Class at the Univeristy of California Extension at Santa Cruz. There are also typescripts of lecture notes, a lecture recording on one sound cassette, and supply lists for drawing, collage, color and design, textile and batik, and Notan art classes. Writings include typescripts by Boswell "Rainbow Street" and "Une Nuit de Brume," and writings by others.
  - Diaries, 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Diaries, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Journal from Travel in Japan, England, and Mexico; Journal from Travel to London and Paris, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Guest Book for Unidentified Party, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Guest Book for Exhibition "All Kinds of Cats,", 1977 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Guest Book for Bothwell's 80th Birthday Party, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mailing Lists, 1995, undated; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Faculty Lists and Schedules of Classes for the California School of Fine Arts, 1953-1960 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Participant Lists for the Sierra Club Camp, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Membership List for the Northern California Chapter of the Artists Equity Association, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Chaparral Membership List, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Lists of Students for the Ansel Adams Yosemite Workshop, 1965-1977, undated; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
  - Lists of Students and Schedule for the Creative Images Class at the University of California Extension at Santa Cruz, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Lists of Students, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Typescripts and Supply Lists for Monotype and Serigraphy Classes, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Typescript and Supply List for Notan Classes, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Typescripts and Class Lists for Drawing Classes, 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Typescripts and Supply Lists for Collage Classes, 1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Typescripts and Supply Lists for Color and Design Classes, 1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Typescripts and Supply Lists for Textile and Batik Classes, 1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Design Lecture Notes from the Schaeffer School, 1959-1960; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 43-45)
  - Lecture 1 at San Francisco Art Institute, 1996; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of Lecture 1 at San Francisco Art Institute, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Transcript of Lecture 2 at San Francisco Art Institute, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Documents concerning Lecture 1and 2 at San Francisco Art Institute, 1996; Includes 1 floppy disk. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Typescript "Rainbow Street" by Dorr Bothwell, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Typescript "Une Nuit de Brume" by Dorr Bothwell, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Writings by Dorr Bothwell, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1996-1998, undated; (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 51-56)
  - Miscellaneous Writings by Others, 1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Oversized Guest Book for Bothwell's 90th Birthday Party, 1988-1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Artwork, 1920-1994; Series 5; (Box 4-5, 13, 16, 17, 11; 1.5 linear feet)
  Artwork consists of 19 sketchbooks including one with daily drawings of her preparations for World War II. Also found are 4 albums of artwork which include primarily ink and pencil drawings and sketches but also include some printed material and correspondence.There are also miscellaneous drawings, collages, a serigraph, an etching by Martha Jackson, and a drawing by Charles Howard.
  - Sketchbook 1, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Sketchbook 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Sketchbook 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Sketchbook 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Sketchbook 5, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks 6 and 7, 1942-1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 8, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 9, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 10, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbooks 11 and 12, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook 13, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook 14, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook 15, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook 16, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook 17, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook 18, 1971-1977 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 19, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Drawings, 1936-1994; (3 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 11) (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - Collages, undated; Oversized material housed in Box 16, Folder 2 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Serigraphs It's Time for a Change, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Etching by Martha Jackson; Drawing by Charles Howard, 1956, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Printed Copies of Albums, undated; 1928-1929 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Artwork Album 1, 1920; 1930; undated; 1939 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Artwork Album 2, 1937; undated; 1929-1932 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Artwork Album 3, undated; 1921-1922; 1930-1931; 1928; 1942 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Artwork Album 4, 1931; undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Prints, 1950; undated; 1952 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Three Oversized Drawings, undated; from Box 5, Folders 12 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - One Oversized Collage, undated; from Box 5, Folder 15 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1926-1979; Series 6; (Box 5, 11-12; 0.5 folders)
  Three scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, programs, and photographs of art work.
  - Scrapbook 3, 1940-1979 (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 1, 1926-1944 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 2, 1945-1952 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1923-2000; Series 7; (Box 5-7, 12, 13; 1.8 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of clippings and exhibition announcements and catalogs that span Bothwell's entire career. Also included are press releases, brochures for art classes, the sale of art work, travel, and camera equipment, reproductions of art work, picture postcards, programs, and miscellaneous commercial business cards. There are also several books including Good Neighbor Color Book: Carlos and Conchita in Coffeeland, illustrated by Bothwell.
  - Clippings, 1925-2000, undated; (28 folders) (Box 5, Folder 21-48)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1925-1946, undated; (6 folders) (Box 5, Folder 49-54)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1947-1997; (28 folders; Oversized materials housed in Box 12) (Box 6, Folder 1-28)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1951-2000, undated undated; (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 29-33)
  - Press Releases, 1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Brochures for Art Classes, 1923-1999, undated; (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 35-39)
  - Brochures for the Sale of Artwork, 1942-1991, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Brochures for Books, 1972-1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Camping Brochures, 1955, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Travel Brochures and Maps, 1951-1972, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 43-44)
  - Brochures for Camera Equipment and Clocks, 1983, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1982-1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Programs and Ticket Stubs, 1953-1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Passenger Lists, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Commercial Business Cards, undated; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 8-10)
  - Book Good Neighbor Color Book: Carlos and Conchita in Coffeeland, illustrated by Dorr Bothwell, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Book Painting and Sculpture by the San Francisco Art Association, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Book Hopscotch by Patricia Evans, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Book A Period of Exploration: San Francisco 1945-1950 by Mary Fuller McChesney, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Book Fox and Hare by Chester Anderson, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Book The Singing Tree by Tony Buttitta and Monica York, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - African Sketchbook Booklet, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalog, 1986; from Box 6, Folder 26 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1900-2001; Series 8; (Box 7-9, 10; 2.4 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Bothwell, her mother and brother, her studio/residences in Mendocino and Joshua Tree, California, and in Apache Junction, Arizona, art classes conducted by Bothwell, events including a reception for Danish royalty in Cheverny, France, and of miscellaneous friends and colleagues including her former husband, sculptor Donal Hord, and friend Francis Cooke. There are also photographs and slides of art work including Bothwell's murals for the Valencia Hotel in La Jolla, and for Manning's Coffee Restaurant, miscellaneous paintings, serigraphs, and collages, exhibition installations, and art work by others. Travel photographs and slides are of scenes in New York, California, Mexico, the Caribbean, France, Italy, Corsica, Spain, the Pacific Islands, Western Nigeria, and China. Miscellaneous photographs and slides are of various forms in nature including trees, fruit, flowers, rock formations, and animals that Bothwell would incorporate into her art work.
  - Dorr Bothwell, her Mother and Brother, 1900-1911 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Dorr Bothwell, 1922-1994; (19 folders) (Box 7, Folder 20-38)
  - Bothwell with Miscellaneous Friends, 1941-1998, undated; (20 folders) (Box 7, Folder 39-58)
  - Memorial Service for Bothwell, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Photograph Album 1, 1968-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Photograph Album 2, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Photograph Album 3, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Bothwell's Mendocino Studio/Residence, 1962-1976, undated; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 63-65)
  - Construction of Bothwell's Joshua Tree Studio/Residence, 1975; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 66-67)
  - Bothwell's Joshua Tree Studio/Residence, 1980-1992, undated; (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 68-71)
  - Scenery Near Joshua Tree, California, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Bothwell's Apache Junction Studio/Residence, 1993-1998, undated; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 73-75)
  - Photographs of an Unidentified Parade, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Reception for the King and Queen of Denmark in Cheverny, France, 1949-1950; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs of Art Classes Conducted by Bothwell, 1948-1983, undated; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Exhibition Installation at Bay Window Gallery, Mendocino, California, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition "Early Work (1940-1950) in Moss Gallery,", 1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Installations at Bothwell's Mendocino Studio, 1988-1992; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous Exhibition Installations, 1993-1999; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 10-12)
  - Album 4: Slides of World Travel, 1947-1991; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 13-16)
  - Slides of Travel in New York, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Photographs and Slides of Travel in California, 1947-1991, undated; (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 18-24)
  - Photographs and Slides of Travel to France, 1948-1966, undated; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 25-29)
  - Photographs and Slides of Travel to Italy, 1948-1990; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 30-31)
  - Slides of Travel to the Caribbean, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Slides of Travel to Corsica, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Slides of Travel to Spain, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Slides of Travel in the Pacific Islands, 1964-1974 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Travel to Western Nigeria, 1968; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 36-37)
  - Album 5: Photographs of Travel to Mexico, 1987; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 38-40)
  - Slides of Travel to China, 1982; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 41-43)
  - Miscellaneous Travel Photographs and Slides, 1976-1993, undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Photographs and Slides of Native Americans, 1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Slides of Rock Formations, 1953-1979 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Slides of Trees, 1955-1972 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Slides of Flowers, 1957-1983; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 48-50)
  - Photograph and Slides of Fruit, 1960-1982 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Slides of Animals, 1961-1972 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Photographs "Designs of Mendocino and Elsewhere,", 1952-1982; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 53-55)
  - Album 6: Photographs of Artwork Executed Between, 1941-1944, undated (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Album 7: Photographs of Miscellaneous Art Work, 1992, undated (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Photographs of Artwork Labeled "Travel Photos Text,", undated (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1962-2001, undated; (26 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-26)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1962-2001, undated; (8 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - Slides of Artwork, 1962-2001, undated (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Digital Photographs of Artwork, 1962-2001, undated; Includes 8 electronic discs (CD-R). (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs of Murals in the "Lolita" Cocktail Room of the Valencia Hotel, La Jolla, California, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Murals in Manning's Coffee Restaurant, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Murals, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Art Work by Others, undated; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - Sets of Negative Strips, undated; (10 folders) (Box 10, Folder 14-23)